<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>LV → Panettone</title>
		<link>https://liamvennerholm.github.io</link>
		<description>Liam Vennerholm’s Panettone blog.</description>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<atom:link href="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/panettone.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml">

		<item>
			<title>On Descriptivism and Domestication</title>
			<pubDate>Thursday, 20 Feb 2025 23:55:00 CST</pubDate>
			<guid>20eb116e-679e-41be-8085-4f29ed46ec26</guid>
			<link>https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/posts/panettone/on_descriptivism_and_domestication.html</link>
			<description><![CDATA[

                <p><span id="dropcap">L</span>inguistic concepts map nicely onto architecture, as illustrated by the postmodernists. But semiotics is not the only example of this. In linguistics, people often discuss descriptivism vs. prescriptivism <small>(this concept isn’t exclusive to linguistics, but it is very prominent in linguistic circles)</small>. One version of this discussion is about whether or not dictionaries are meant to strictly define a word or record how that word is most commonly used. Many linguists are not interested in enforcing a “correct” way to use a given language, they’re merely interested in the observation of language in use, in the wild. It’s more about learning how people use language by watching and documenting—<em>describing</em>—rather than telling them the rights and wrongs of grammar—<em>prescribing</em>.</p>

                <p>This makes me think about Louis Kahn’s conversation with a brick in the 2003 documentary <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0373175/"><em>My Architect</em> by Nathaniel Kahn</a>.</p>

                <blockquote>
                    <p>“If you think of Brick, you say to Brick, ‘What do you want, Brick?’ And Brick says to you, ‘I like an arch.’ And if you say to Brick, ‘Look, arches are expensive, and I can use a concrete lintel over you. What do you think of that, Brick?’ Brick says, ‘I like an arch.’ And it’s important, you see, that you honor the material that you use … You can only do it if you honor the brick and glorify the brick instead of shortchanging it.”</p>
                </blockquote>

                <p>Louis Kahn called this idea “existence will.” The existence will of a brick is the state the brick wants to be in. It is more brick-like to be an arch than to be a lintel. This is because of the brick’s inherent properties: its size, its shape, its proportions, its materiality. To make a lintel you would either have to change the brick (e.g. jack arches and their fanned-out, skewed brick shapes; though even then, it’s still an arch) or, as in Kahn’s words above, avoid brick altogether and just use concrete. This tension is the existence will of the brick. The easiest path forward forces an arch.</p>

                <p>In thermodynamics, the idea of entropy can be understood similarly. Entropy is commonly conceived as the tendency of everything in the universe toward decay, but there’s another, more intuitive understanding of entropy that I think is germane to this discussion of existence will. Rather than being a tendency toward decay, entropy can differently be understood as a tendency toward a state where energy is spread out evenly rather than a state where energy is concentrated. For example, a warm coffee mug tends to cool down in an environment that’s cooler than it, and in turn the environment around it gets slightly warmer until the mug and the environment are the same temperature. In other words, energy that’s concentrated (the warm mug in a cool environment) tends to spread out (the mug cooling down) until equilibrium is reached and the whole system is at rest (the mug and the environment it’s in are the same temperature). This way of thinking about entropy is similar to Kahn’s idea of existence will. The brick arch is a lower entropy system than the concrete lintel. It’s the path of least resistance.</p>

                <p>I’ve encountered a similar existence will/entropy in Panettone. As a part of this project, I wanted to take Panettone from its habitat of being street furniture and turn it into home furniture. I wanted to <em>domesticate</em> Panettone. This, I decided, would involve creating one. At first, I just started with trying to make one exactly as is, concrete and all, but I very quickly ran into issues. It turns out, a concrete object of this size weighs over 400 pounds and isn’t easy to make. I quickly tried to think of ways to fight this and make it more practical but still concrete. I tried designing it to be made of a lighter weight concrete and with a hollow center, but it would still be over 200 pounds. But then I realized that maybe this isn’t something I should fight. Maybe Panettone should change based on the habitat. After all, the process of domestication is one of change and adaptation.</p>

                <p>This realization made me think of descriptivism, entropy, and especially Kahn’s existence will. Though there is one critical difference between this and existence will. In the case of existence will, the brick is the agent enacting a force on the situation: it wants to be an arch. However, in the case of the domestication, the new habitat is the agent enacting a force on Panettone: Panettone must adapt to its environment.</p>

                <p>It’s my intention with this project to study that process of adaptation. The creatures of earth came to be through a process of being shaped by their environments; I aim to learn more about the same process in the environments we and our objects live in.</p>

			]]></description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>Beginning</title>
			<pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 01:22:00 CST</pubDate>
			<guid>5c7d191f-61ef-4cb7-8d0e-465382772dcb</guid>
			<link>https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/posts/panettone/beginning.html</link>
			<description><![CDATA[

                <p><span class="dropcap">A</span>n idea in design that I’m passionate about in is the idea that the designed objects around us are active participants in our lives—creatures that live alongside us—not just a part of the backdrop on which we live our lives. They aren’t lifeless, inanimate tools that only exist to serve us. They live life with us and we develop relationships with them. Maybe you have a boat that you’ve named, maybe as a child you confided in your favorite plush frog, maybe you mourned moving out of a beloved house like you might mourn the loss of a loved one. They may not be a form of biotic life, but the things we live with feel like they’re some version of alive.</p>

                <p>As a designer, I find it exciting to try and affect this more directly in my work. One way of doing that is by creating something that resembles a living thing (e.g., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Duck">a building that looks like a duck</a>), but using zoomorphic forms is not the only way of giving life to the things we design. Another way is to make them behave like living creatures; maybe there is a suggestion of movement or emotion. Well, I saw an example of this about 3 years ago now, and ever since then, it’s become a bit of an obsession.</p>

            <hr>

                <p>Of all things that I thought might seem to have some life to them, traffic bollards were not near the top of the list. Why would they be? Their only purpose is to solve mundane vehicular traffic issues. During my study abroad in Italy during the summer of 2022, I received an answer to that question in the form of multitudes of knee-height, gumdrop-shaped, concrete companions.</p>

				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/08.jpeg" alt="A group of small, yellow, concrete bollards.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/10.jpeg" alt="Two small, yellow, concrete bollards. One is in the grass, the other is in a small area where the curb of the street cuts back, as if it’s a little nook just for the bollard.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/16.jpeg" alt="A view down a fork in the road in Como, Italy. Coming toward the viewer is a staggered row of small, yellow, concrete bollards.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/17.jpeg" alt="A small, bare concrete bollard sitting next to a bike rack.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/24.jpeg" alt="A small, concrete bollard that looks it used to be painted yellow, but the paint has worn away.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/31.jpeg" alt="A view crossing a crosswalk in Como, Italy. There is a building on the right and a busy roas on the left. On the sidewalk on the other site of the crosswalk, there are two small, concrete bollards with weathered yellow paint jobs holding up a large, blue street sign together.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/35.jpeg" alt="In the middle of a street in Como, Italy stands a small, yellow, concrete bollard holding up a “do not enter” sign.">
                <figcaption><em>Photos of the bollards I took while in Italy</em></figcaption>


                <p>Sometimes gathered in herds, other times all by their lonesome, these stoic creatures have a certain visual mobility to them that contradicts the immense weight of their concrete construction. Unlike their American counterparts which are usually affixed to the ground in stiff, straight lines, these bollards are free to move around like traffic cones <small>(though they’re quite a bit heavier than traffic cones)</small>. In fact, part of what makes them seem so alive is that they're never in a perfectly straight line. It seems as if they’re living their little bollard lives, but then as you turn and look at them, they freeze in place.</p>

                <p>Like the creatures of the animal kingdom, they have shared physical characteristics, such as a small stature, canted sides, and an overall domed profile, but they also exhibit a certain amount of genetic diversity. Most of the time, if they’re not left as bare concrete, you’ll find them sporting a yellow coloration, but you might also find them in shades of blue, green, red, and many other colors—you might even find them wearing stripes. Another notable difference is the job that the bollard is doing. Some, as I mentioned above, are enlisted as traffic cones, while others dutifully hold up “Do Not Enter” signs. The way they hold up a sign is with an appendage protruding from their crown. These appendages, in addition to holding street signs, are also used to hold up stanchions with chains or ropes stringing along a caravan of bollards.</p>

                <p>Whether their design is intentionally playful or merely just a utilitarian concrete shape designed to easily demold from its formwork, it lends itself to creaturely ideas while also being a blank canvas. In fact, I’m not the only one who sees this; someone else took it upon themselves to make this creaturely demeanor more explicit by painting one to look like a penguin.</p>

                <p>As anonymous as they are, I think these bollards have a lot to say, even if they’re not Italy’s most well known domes.</p>

            <hr>
                
                <p>After getting back from Italy, this bollard obsession continued and found its way in to a couple of my studio projects. I tried to learn more, but searching the internet for “yellow, gumdrop-shaped bollard” doesn’t really turn up with many helpful search results. I didn’t know the name of the bollards or the name of the person who designed them. I assumed that they were an anonymous object that was probably designed by some Italian civil engineer whose name I’d never know.</p>

                <p>Cut to about a year later. I’ve gained a bit of a reputation as the bollard guy among my classmates and professors, and part of that reputation is that people send me pictures of various things that have a resemblance to the shape of the bollards <small>(which is a lot of things; it’s a surprisingly common shape)</small>. In addition to receiving pictures of bollard doppelgängers, I was also helping to start an architecture student publication with my classmates. I decided to write a piece about the bollards as one of my contributions <small>(much of the content of that article has been adapted into what you see above)</small>. One day, as I was writing my bollard article, a friend sent me a photo of the cover of a book in an art museum’s bookstore. It was the cover for <a href="https://shop.walkerart.org/museum-shop/products/the-paradox-of-stillness-art-object-and-performance"><em>The Paradox of Stillness: Art, Object, and Performance</em></a> which depicts five dome-shaped friends, each painted a different color, sitting on a concrete floor. I had never seen these bollards before, so I looked up the book to learn more … and learn more I did.</p>

                <img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/paradox_of_stillness.webp" alt="The book cover for ‘The Paradox of Stillness: Art, Object, and Performance’ which depicts five small objects shaped suspiciously like the aforementioned bollards on a smooth concrete floor.">
                <a href="https://shop.walkerart.org/museum-shop/products/the-paradox-of-stillness-art-object-and-performance"><figcaption><em>The Paradox of Stillness: Art, Object, and Performance by Félix González-Torres, Oskar Schlemmer, Robert Morris and more</em></figcaption></a>

                <p>These book cover bollards aren’t our beloved Milanese companions; they’re a series of small mobile sculptures made by the artist Robert Breer. Concealed inside their brightly colored domes are mechanisms that move them very slowly across the floor of an art gallery; Breer called them “floats.”</p>

                <p>While learning about Breer’s floats, I found familiar image of a small concrete bollard on a street in Milan. This image led me to <a href="https://www.designboom.com/design/  giulio-iacchetti-bard-furniture-tribute-milan-03-19-2014/">an article about Italian designer Giulio Iacchetti</a>. The image in question was not of the bollard I hoped to learn about but of a work by Iacchetti paying homage to the same bollard. It turns out I am not the only one with an affinity for these guys. But alas, just as I realized this, I see the long-awaited name of the father of these bollards. After a year of searching and searching and eventually losing hope, I had accepted that I probably would never learn the name of this anonymous designer. I thought all hope was lost, but just at that moment, I saw the name of … Enzo Mari? It was Enzo Mari the whole time? Yes. It was Enzo Mari the whole time.</p>

            <hr>
                
                <p>In 1980, the city of Milan needed a quick and simple solution for traffic issues they were having, so they called up Milanese designer Enzo Mari to help. Mari developed a traffic bollard that he named “Panettone.” Their shape is in reference to their namesake: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panettone">the panettone cake</a>. Traditionally eaten at Christmas time, the iconic domed cylindrical panettone fruit cake is a staple of Milan. Instead of fruit and cake, Mari’s Panettone is made of coarse aggregate and cement and is not nearly as delicious. It is a simple, precast concrete jack of all trades. It can do the jobs of a bollard, a traffic cone, a signage stand, a stanchion base, and an impromptu seat for weary pedestrians. Unlike the cake, the bollards weigh around 200kg (~440lbs) each, putting a big asterisk on their ability to be moved easily; that is, they technically <em>can</em> be moved but really only with the aid of equipment. They were originally intended as a short-term solution, but they ended up sticking around after being released onto the streets of Milan; like their love for the Christmas cake, the Milanese grew quite fond of their new concrete friends.</p>

                <p>Upon a closer look, some Panettoni have canted sides while others’ sides are vertical. Perhaps this can be chalked up to a slouching problem, but I think it’s more than that. Those with canted sides also tend to have newer, more vibrant paint jobs compared to the weathered, dull ones of the bollards with perfectly vertical sides. My best guess is that the older generation of bollards—that is the more weathered ones—don’t have canted sides, but as soon as Milan decided they were here to stay, they had to mass-produce them thus changing the design slightly in favor of a shape that demolds from its formwork more easily, so the form can be reused.</p>

              </div>
                <img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/bard01.jpg" alt="A view of someone standing on Giulio Iacchetti’s ‘Bard’ ottoman to reach a book on a high shelf. It is designed to look like the Panettone bollard, only it’s plush.">
                <a href="https://www.giulioiacchetti.com/?p=2383"><figcaption><em>Bard ottoman by Giulio Iacchetti</em></figcaption></a>

                <p>These Panettoni found their way into the hearts of the Milanese which continues to the present. Giulio Iacchetti, the Italian industrial designer I mentioned earlier, has paid homage to Mari’s icon in a couple of his designs. In 2014, he designed <a href="https://www.giulioiacchetti.com/?p=2383">Bard</a>, a plush ottoman that owes its image to the Panettone bollard which owes <em>its</em> image to the Christmas cake. It is the same size and shape as Mari’s, only this time it’s plush. Iacchetti also designed a small Panettone-shaped paperweight called <a href="https://www.giulioiacchetti.com/?p=6539">Medhelan</a> in September 2021.</p>

				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/Snow_Mari/01.jpg" alt="Claude Everett’s ‘Snow Mari’ on day 0, freshly created and unmelted.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/Snow_Mari/02.jpg" alt="Claude Everett’s ‘Snow Mari’ on day 1, having survived a few kicks and some slight melting.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/Snow_Mari/03.jpg" alt="Claude Everett’s ‘Snow Mari’ on day 2, slightly more melted than the day before.">
				<img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/Snow_Mari/04.jpg" alt="Claude Everett’s ‘Snow Mari’ on day 3, gone.">
                <a href="https://claudeverett.org/snow-mari/"><figcaption><em>Snow Mari by Claud Everett</em></figcaption></a>

                <p>Claud Everett, another designer in Milan, runs an Instagram page called <a href="https://www.instagram.com/maripanettone/">@maripanettone</a>, an archive of Panettoni and Panettone-shaped objects. Additionally, in 2014, Everett catalogued an interesting encounter with a Panettone or “Mari,” as he calls them. On a walking trail in Northern Italy, he found a lone Mari where there should be two according to all the other entrances to that path. He shortly found that the other had fallen into a nearby river. He constructed a <a href="https://claudeverett.org/snow-mari/">Snow Mari</a> to fill the void next to the lonely one, and then came back daily to document its condition. It only lasted 3 days before it melted.</p>

                <img src="https://liamvennerholm.github.io/blog/panettone/images/SA2022/30.jpeg" alt="A Panettone bollard painted to look like a blue penguin by street artist Pao.">
                <a href="https://www.paopao.it/en/"><figcaption><em>Street art by Pao, photo by me</em></figcaption></a>

                <p>The Italian street artist <a href="https://www.paopao.it/en/">Pao</a> uses Panettoni as the canvas for his art. He paints them to look like different characters from pop culture, though usually they’re penguins. <small>My favorite one he’s painted looks like R2-D2</small>.</p>

                <p>Not only am I not the only one who is interested in these Panettoni, I’m also not the only one who sees some sort of animism in them. Pao’s penguins, Claude Everett’s Snow Mari, and Guilio Iacchetti’s Bard all get at a deeper empathy and companionship that is to be found with these bollards. With this blog, I’d like to explore my own relationship with the Panettone bollard and hopefully reveal something of value along the way.</p>

			]]></description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>